When a movement includes in its discourse language around gender equality, it increases dramatically the chances it will adopt nonviolence, and thus, the likelihood it will succeed. The research squared up with my own documentation of political organizing in Israel and Palestine. I've noticed that movements which welcome women into leadership positions, such as the one I documented in a village called Budrus, were much more likely to achieve their goals. This village was under a real threat of being wiped off the map when Israel started building the separation barrier. The proposed route would require the destruction of this community's olive groves, their cemeteries and would ultimately enclose the village from all sides. Through inspired local leadership, they launched a nonviolent resistance campaign to stop that from happening. The odds were massively stacked against them. But they had a secret weapon: a 15-year-old girl who courageously jumped in front of a bulldozer which was about to uproot an olive tree, stopping it. In that moment, the community of Budrus realized what was possible if they welcomed and encouraged women to participate in public life. And so it was that the women of Budrus went to the front lines day after day, using their creativity and acumen to overcome multiple obstacles they faced in a 10-month unarmed struggle.
Cuando un movimiento incluye en su discurso un lenguaje de igualdad de género, aumenta drásticamente la posibilidad de que adopte la no violencia, y por lo tanto, la probabilidad de éxito. La investigación encaja con mi propia documentación de la organización política en Israel y Palestina. He visto que los movimientos que acogen a las mujeres en posiciones de liderazgo, como el que he documentado en un pueblo llamado Budrus, eran mucho más propensos a alcanzar sus objetivos. Este pueblo estaba bajo una amenaza real de ser borrado del mapa cuando Israel inició la construcción del muro de separación. La ruta propuesta requería la destrucción de los olivos de esta comunidad, sus cementerios y, en última instancia, cerrar el pueblo desde todos los lados. Por un inspirado liderazgo local, lanzaron una campaña de resistencia no violenta para evitar que eso sucediera. Las probabilidades estaban masivamente en contra de ellos. Pero tenían un arma secreta: una niña de 15 años que con valor saltó delante de una excavadora que estaba a punto de arrancar un árbol de olivo, deteniéndola. En ese momento, la comunidad de Budrus se dio cuenta de lo que era posible si le daban bienvenida y confianza a las mujeres a participar en la vida pública. Y así fue que las mujeres de Budrus fueron día a día a las líneas del frente, usando su creatividad y visión para superar los obstáculos que enfrentaron en una lucha sin armas de 10 meses.
And as you can probably tell at this point, they win at the end. The separation barrier was changed completely to the internationally recognized green line, and the women of Budrus came to be known across the West Bank for their indomitable energy. (Applause) Thank you. I want to pause for a second, which you helped me do, because I do want to tackle two very serious misunderstandings that could happen at this point. The first one is that I don't believe women are inherently or essentially more peaceful than men. But I do believe that in today's world, women experience power differently. Having had to navigate being in the less powerful position in multiple aspects of their lives, women are often more adept at how to surreptitiously pressure for change against large, powerful actors. The term "manipulative," often charged against women in a derogatory way, reflects a reality in which women have often had to find ways other than direct confrontation to achieve their goals. And finding alternatives to direct confrontation is at the core of nonviolent resistance. Now to the second potential misunderstanding. I've been talking a lot about my experiences in the Middle East, and some of you might be thinking now that the solution then is for us to educate Muslim and Arab societies to be more inclusive of their women. If we were to do that, they would be more successful. They do not need this kind of help. Women have been part of the most influential movements coming out of the Middle East, but they tend to be invisible to the international community. Our cameras are largely focused on the men who often end up involved in the more confrontational scenes that we find so irresistible in our news cycle. And we end up with a narrative that not only erases women from the struggles in the region but often misrepresents the struggles themselves. In the late 1980s, an uprising started in Gaza, and quickly spread to the West Bank and East Jerusalem. It came to be known as the First Intifada, and people who have any visual memory of it
Y como seguramente se puede decir en este punto, ganaron al final. La barrera de separación se cambió por completo a la línea verde reconocida internacionalmente, y las mujeres de Budrus llegaron a ser conocidas por toda Cisjordania por su energía indomable. (Aplausos) Gracias. Quiero parar un segundo, si me permiten, porque quiero abordar dos malentendidos muy graves que podrían darse en este punto. El primero de ellos es que no creo que las mujeres sean intrínseca o esencialmente más pacíficas que los hombres. Pero sí creo que en el mundo actual, las mujeres experimentan el poder de manera diferente. Después de tener que navegar en la posición menos poderosa en varios aspectos de su vida, las mujeres suelen ser más hábiles en la forma de presionar subrepticiamente para el cambio contra actores grandes y potentes. El término "manipuladora", muchas veces usado contra las mujeres despectivamente, refleja una realidad en la que las mujeres a menudo han tenido que encontrar maneras distintas a las de confrontación directa para lograr sus objetivos. Y la búsqueda de alternativas a la confrontación directa es el núcleo de la resistencia no violenta. Ahora el segundo posible malentendido. He hablado mucho de mis experiencias en Oriente Medio, y algunos podrían estar pensando ahora que nuestra solución es entonces educar a las sociedades musulmanas y árabes para que incluyan más a sus mujeres. Si tuviéramos que hacer eso, ellos tendrían más éxito. Ellos no necesitan este tipo de ayuda. Las mujeres han sido parte de los movimientos más influyentes de Oriente Medio, pero tienden a ser invisibles para la comunidad internacional. Nuestras cámaras se centran principalmente en los hombres que a menudo terminan involucrados en las escenas más polémicas que encontramos tan irresistibles en las noticias. Y terminamos con una narrativa que no solo borra a las mujeres de las luchas en la región sino que con frecuencia falsifica las propias luchas. A finales de 1980, comenzó un levantamiento en Gaza, y se extendió rápidamente a Cisjordania y Jerusalén Este. Llegó a ser conocido como la Primera Intifada, y quienes tienen alguna memoria visual de la misma
generally conjure up something like this: Palestinian men throwing rocks at Israeli tanks. The news coverage at the time made it seem like stones, Molotov cocktails and burning tires were the only activities taking place in the Intifada. This period, though, was also marked by widespread nonviolent organizing in the forms of strikes, sit-ins and the creation of parallel institutions. During the First Intifada, whole sectors of the Palestinian civilian population mobilized, cutting across generations, factions and class lines. They did this through networks of popular committees, and their use of direct action and communal self-help projects challenged Israel's very ability to continue ruling the West Bank and Gaza. According to the Israeli Army itself, 97 percent of activities during the First Intifada were unarmed. And here's another thing that is not part of our narrative about that time. For 18 months in the Intifada, women were the ones calling the shots behind the scenes: Palestinian women from all walks of life in charge of mobilizing hundreds of thousands of people in a concerted effort to withdraw consent from the occupation. Naela Ayesh, who strived to build a self-sufficient Palestinian economy by encouraging women in Gaza to grow vegetables in their backyards, an activity deemed illegal by the Israeli authorities at that time; Rabeha Diab, who took over decision-making authority for the entire uprising when the men who had been running it were deported; Fatima Al Jaafari, who swallowed leaflets containing the uprising's directives in order to spread them across the territories without getting caught; and Zahira Kamal, who ensured the longevity of the uprising by leading an organization that went from 25 women to 3,000 in a single year. Despite their extraordinary achievements, none of these women have made it into our narrative of the First Intifada. We do this in other parts of the globe, too. In our history books, for instance, and in our collective consciousness, men are the public faces and spokespersons for the 1960s struggle for racial justice in the United States. But women were also a critical driving force, mobilizing, organizing, taking to the streets. How many of us think of Septima Clark when we think of the United States Civil Rights era? Remarkably few. But she played a crucial role in every phase of the struggle, particularly by emphasizing literacy and education. She's been omitted, ignored, like so many other women who played critical roles in the United States Civil Rights Movement. This is not about getting credit. It's more profound than that. The stories we tell matter deeply to how we see ourselves, and to how we believe movements are run and how movements are won. The stories we tell about a movement like the First Intifada or the United States Civil Rights era matter deeply and have a critical influence in the choices Palestinians, Americans and people around the world will make next time they encounter an injustice and develop the courage to confront it. If we do not lift up the women who played critical roles in these struggles, we fail to offer up role models to future generations. Without role models, it becomes harder for women to take up their rightful space in public life. And as we saw earlier, one of the most critical variables in determining whether a movement will be successful or not is a movement's ideology regarding the role of women in public life. This is a question of whether we're moving towards more democratic and peaceful societies. In a world where so much change is happening, and where change is bound to continue at an increasingly faster pace, it is not a question of whether we will face conflict, but rather a question of which stories will shape how we choose to wage conflict. Thank you. (Applause)
generalmente evocan algo como esto: hombres palestinos que lanzan piedras a los tanques israelíes. La cobertura del momento hacía parecer como si piedras, cócteles molotov y neumáticos en llamas fueron las únicas actividades que tenían lugar en la Intifada. Sin embargo, también estuvo marcada por una organización no violenta generalizada en forma de huelgas, sentadas y creación de instituciones paralelas. Durante la primera Intifada, sectores enteros de la población civil palestina se movilizaron, a través de generaciones, facciones y clases. Lo hicieron a través de redes de comités populares, y su uso de la acción directa y proyectos de autoayuda comunales desafiado la propia capacidad de Israel de seguir gobernando Cisjordania y Gaza. Según el propio ejército israelí, el 97 % de los activistas durante la primera Intifada estaban desarmados. Y aquí hay otra cosa que no es parte de nuestro relato sobre ese tiempo. Durante los 18 meses de la Intifada, las mujeres eran las que mandaban detrás de escena: mujeres palestinas de todo tipo estaban a cargo de la movilización de cientos de miles de personas en un esfuerzo concertado para retirar el consentimiento de la ocupación. Naela Ayyash, que se esforzó por crear una economía palestina autosuficiente alentando a las mujeres en Gaza a cultivar hortalizas en sus jardines, una actividad considerada ilegal por las autoridades israelíes en ese momento; Rabeha Diab, que se hizo cargo de la autoridad de toma de decisiones de todo el levantamiento cuando los hombres que habían estado haciéndolo fueron deportados; Fatima Al Jaafari, que tragó volantes con las directivas del levantamiento para difundirlos por todos los territorios sin ser descubierta; y Zahira Kamal, que aseguró la perdurabilidad del levantamiento liderando una organización que pasó de 25 mujeres a 3000 en un solo año. A pesar de sus logros extraordinarios, ninguna de estas mujeres ha estado en nuestra narrativa de la Primera Intifada. Hacemos esto en otras partes del mundo, también. En los libros de historia, por ejemplo, y en nuestra conciencia colectiva, los hombres son las caras visibles y los portavoces de la década de lucha de 1960 por la justicia racial en EE. UU. Pero las mujeres también eran una fuerza impulsora fundamental, movilizando, organizando, tomando las calles. ¿Cuántos de nosotros pensamos en Septima Clark cuando pensamos en la era de Derechos Civiles de EE. UU.? Realmente pocos. Pero ella jugó un papel crucial en todas las fases de la lucha, sobre todo haciendo hincapié en la alfabetización y la educación. Ella ha sido omitida, ignorada, como tantas otras mujeres que desempeñaron un papel crítico en el Movimiento de Derechos Civiles de EE. UU. No se trata de obtener crédito. Es más profundo que eso. Las historias que contamos impactan profundamente nuestra forma de vernos, y cómo creemos que se manejan los movimientos y cómo se ganan los movimientos. Las historias que hablan de movimientos como la Primera Intifada o la era de Derechos Civiles de EE. UU. impactan profundamente y tienen una influencia crítica en la elección que los palestinos, los estadounidenses y la gente de todo el mundo hará la próxima vez que encuentren una injusticia y se armen de valor para enfrentarse a ella. Si no elevamos a las mujeres que ejecutan un papel crítico en estas luchas, no podremos ofrecer modelos para las generaciones futuras. Sin modelos de conducta, se hace más difícil que las mujeres ocupen el espacio que les corresponde en la vida pública. Y como hemos visto antes, una de las variables más críticas para determinar si un movimiento tendrá éxito o no es la ideología de un movimiento con respecto al papel de las mujeres en la vida pública. Esta es una cuestión de si nos estamos moviendo hacia sociedades más democráticas y pacíficas. En un mundo donde ocurren tantos cambios, y donde el cambio está obligado a continuar a un ritmo cada vez más rápido, no es una cuestión de si vamos a hacer frente a los conflictos, sino más bien una cuestión de qué historias modelarán la forma que elegiremos para librar conflictos. Gracias. (Aplausos)